Profile of President Shri Ram Nath Kovind

Posted On: 25 JUL 2017 1:14PM by PIB Delhi

A lawyer, veteran political representative and long-time advocate of egalitarianism and integrity in Indian public life and society, Shri Ram Nath Kovind was born on October 1, 1945, in Paraunkh, near Kanpur, Uttar Pradesh. His parents were Shri Maiku Lal and Smt Kalawati.

Before assuming charge of the office of the 14th President of India on July 25, 2017, Shri Kovind served as the 36th Governor of the state of Bihar from August 16, 2015, to June 20, 2017.

Educational and Professional Background

Shri Kovind completed his school education in Kanpur and obtained the degrees of B.Com and L.L.B. from Kanpur University. In 1971, he enrolled as an Advocate with the Bar Council of Delhi.

Shri Kovind was Union Government Advocate in the Delhi High Court from 1977 to 1979 and Union Government Standing Counsel in the Supreme Court from 1980 to 1993. He became Advocate-on-Record of the Supreme Court of India in 1978. He practised at the Delhi High Court and Supreme Court for 16 years till 1993.

Parliamentary and Public Life

Shri Kovind was elected as a member of the Rajya Sabha from Uttar Pradesh in April 1994. He served for two consecutive terms of six years each till March 2006. Shri Kovind served on various Parliamentary Committees like Parliamentary Committee on Welfare of Scheduled Castes/Tribes; Parliamentary Committee on Home Affairs; Parliamentary Committee on Petroleum and Natural Gas; Parliamentary Committee on Social Justice and Empowerment; and Parliamentary Committee on Law and Justice. He was Chairman of the Rajya Sabha House Committee.

Shri Kovind also served as Member of the Board of Management of the Dr B.R Ambedkar University, Lucknow, and Member of the Board of Governors of the Indian Institute of Management, Kolkata. He was part of the Indian delegation at the United Nations and addressed the United Nations General Assembly in October 2002.

Positions Held

2015-17: Governor of Bihar

1994-2006: Member of the Rajya Sabha, representing the state of Uttar Pradesh

1971-75 and 1981: General Secretary, Akhil Bharatiya Koli Samaj

1977-79: Union Government Advocate at the Delhi High Court

1982-84: Union Government Junior Counsel in the Supreme Court

Personal Details

Shri Kovind married Smt Savita Kovind on May 30, 1974. They have a son, Shri Prashant Kumar, and a daughter, Miss Swati. An avid reader, the President has keen interest in reading books on politics and social change, law and history, and religion.

During his long public career, Shri Kovind has travelled widely across the country. He has also visited Thailand, Nepal, Pakistan, Singapore, Germany, Switzerland, France, the United Kingdom and the United States in his capacity as a Member of Parliament.

AKT/HS

(Release ID: 1497014) Visitor Counter: 200









n